<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>SophoMorgan</title>
    <description>The philosophy blog of Morgan Laco.
</description>
    <link>sophomorgan.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="sophomorgan.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2016 18:51:47 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2016 18:51:47 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Symbols</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A significant component of human intelligence is our ability to use symbols. In
this article, I would like to discuss a few things about symbols that I think
can sharpen our ability to reason and communicate if we keep them in mind. Most
of these things may be common knowledge, but we can sometimes gain new insights
just by considering a well-known idea in the right context so I would like to
explicitly record them here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-symbol&quot;&gt;What is a symbol?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A symbol is anything with which we mentally associate another object or concept.
It can take many forms, including spoken words, written words, images, and
gestures. Symbols allow us to communicate; we cause others to think of something
by producing the symbol that is associated with it. When a person hears or sees
or otherwise observes a symbol, they tend to think of a particular concept.
Seeing an object can likewise cause you to think of the symbol associated with
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reaction, thinking of a concept when you see a symbol, is a physical
process that takes place in our brain and nervous system as a whole. Being a
physical process mean that it is, to a large degree, deterministic. It also
means that it is dependent on the state of the brain; the particular reaction
that the brain has to a symbol owes to the physical configuration of the brain’s
parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The definition of symbols is arbitrary. “Correctness” of a definition only means
whether it conforms to the definition that someone else chose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-definitions-are-created&quot;&gt;How definitions are created&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recalling that a definition is the effect of a particular physical configuration
in the brain, it follows that a definition is created when that configuration is
formed. Our brains do this automatically; when we see things together frequently,
our brain will naturally form connections that cause us to be more likely to think
of one thing when we see the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is useful to consider two scenarios in which symbols are acquired;
that in which the definition’s object is present, and the other in which it is
not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;object-is-present&quot;&gt;Object is Present&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We acquire many of our first symbols in the presence of the object. For
instance, a parent shows us an apple and says “apple”. Though obvious, it is
worth mentioning that when a symbol is created this way, then it stands for a
real object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;object-is-absent&quot;&gt;Object is Absent&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to define symbols in the absence of their object, we must use other
symbols. This of course requires that we have already learned those symbols. In
contrast to the previous scenario, the symbol’s intended object may not exist,
even if those of its constituent symbols do. For example, horses exist and horns
(such as that on a rhinoceros) exist, but a unicorn, defined as a horned horse,
does not exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the absense of an object, symbols are defined by combining symbols, and
consequently concepts. Each additional symbol or concept can potentially narrow
the set of objects that are described by that combination, or even empty it
completely as in the case of the unicorn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;object-is-simulated&quot;&gt;Object is Simulated&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For completeness, I’ll discuss a third scenario where the image being defined is
absent but simulated in some way. This scenario is, strictly speaking, a subset
of the previous, but it has characteristics not shared by the the rest of the
‘absent’ scenario. By ‘simulated’, I mean that an attempt is made to accurately
reproduce some sensory pattern that the object itself would. Examples of this
are photographs, drawings, sound recordings, or an imitation of a sound the
object makes. These can be very effective ways of defining something so that a
person will be able to recognize and identify the actual object when they
encounter it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chosen-and-consequential-characteristics&quot;&gt;Chosen and Consequential Characteristics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chosen-characteristics&quot;&gt;Chosen Characteristics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is essential in communication to discern between statements that
convey a symbol’s chosen characteristics from those that convey its
consequential characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chosen characteristics are (as you would expect) those that a symbol’s objects
possess &lt;em&gt;because we decided they do&lt;/em&gt;. It might be more accurate to say that we
decided to associate the symbol only with objects that possess these
characteristics. Again, it is possible that &lt;em&gt;there are no objects&lt;/em&gt; with a given
set of characteristics, in which case we would never find an object that we can
correctly associate the symbol with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Talk about chosen characteristics of “Object Present” definitions]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;consequential-characteristics&quot;&gt;Consequential Characteristics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes there are objects that possess the characteristics we chose for a
symbol. In that case, those objects will often have &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; characteristics,
outside the chosen ones. These are what I’m calling &lt;em&gt;consequential
characteristics&lt;/em&gt;. We didn’t intentionally choose to associate the symbol with
objects having these characteristics, it’s just a consequence of our choice. For
example, apples have cells, but people have had a name for them since before we
knew about cells, so that particular characteristic is not chosen, but a
consequential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;implications&quot;&gt;Implications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statements expressing the chosen characteristics defining a symbol do not convey
information about its objects, as those objects might not even exist. Such
statements instead convey information about &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt;; they convey that &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; have
made an association which, again, is a &lt;em&gt;physcal&lt;/em&gt; configuration of our brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It follows that to convey information, we must make statements about the
&lt;em&gt;consequential&lt;/em&gt; characteristics of objects associated with our symbol. This
statement can be as basic as saying that those objects exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also meaningless to ask whether the objects associated a symbol have a
given characteristic when that symbol has no &lt;em&gt;chosen&lt;/em&gt; characteristics, since
without them, the symbol doesn’t refer to anything (or maybe it refers to
anything, which would be equally useless). To understand this, imagine that
someone walks up to you and, without any context, asks “hey, was that thing
green?”. You don’t know what &lt;em&gt;that thing&lt;/em&gt; is, so you can’t possibly know whether
it was green. Yet, since chosen characteristics are what specify a symbols object,
using a symbol without chosen characteristics is exactly like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may seem abstract and unimportant, but I have seen many discussions carried
out where a central term was not defined, or where the participants apparently
had different definitions for it. In many situations, if this problem were
resolved, there would be no disagreement at all. It is as if two people were
having a disagreement about what a painting looked like, while they were not
looking at the same painting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be referencing these ideas about symbols in future posts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>sophomorgan.github.io/2016/06/04/symbols.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">sophomorgan.github.io/2016/06/04/symbols.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
